Guide to the Rural Institute for Inclusive Communities Publications 1977-2017
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Rural Institute for Inclusive Communities publications
1977-2017
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
RG 046
Rural Institute for Inclusive Communities
1.0 linear feet
This collection contains materials including pamphlets, flyers, newsletters and manuals produced by the Rural Institute for Inclusive Communities, which is affiliated with the University of Montana and has as its mission "creating better lives for rural people with disabilities and their families."
Historical Note
Founded in 1978, the Rural Institute for Inclusive Communities was originally called the Montana University Affiliated Program Satellite (MUAPS), and was located at the University of Montana in Missoula. MUAPS was one of 43 university-affiliated programs in the United States that focused on improving and developing services for the developmentally disabled. It was funded through the federal Administration on Developmental Disabilities. In 1990 MUAPS became known as the Montana University Affiliated Rural Institute on Disabilities, and it consolidated with the Research and Training Center on Rural Rehabilitation Services. The Research and Training Center (RTC) was established in October 1987 at the University of Montana to pursue research and training for the purpose of assisting persons with disabilities in rural communities. It was one of 35 centers in the United States funded by the National Institute on Disability and Rehabilitation Research of the federal Department of Education. The consolidation broadened the program’s scope and combined a variety of services such as a new clinic operation.
By the early 2000s, the Institute’s name had changed to the University of Montana Rural Institute, and by 2017 it had become the University of Montana Rural Institute for Inclusive Communities. The Rural Institute’s main focus is to assist existing programs, professionals and individuals who provide services for persons with disabilities in rural areas.
This is a collection of published materials produced by the Rural Institute. Items include newsletters, reports, pamphlets, and instructional manuals. The reports were often prepared jointly with other entities that offered community services to persons with disabilities. The collection also contains copies of the Rural Institute’s Educational Home Model Project child care booklets.
The materials in this collections are arranged chronologically by publication date and then alphabetically by publication title.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
Materials from this collection were removed from the Archives' University Publications collection (UPUBs) in 2016 and placed in their own collection.
Publications were acquired from a variety of sources, including the Rural Institute.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Rural Institute for Inclusive Communities--Archives; Montana University Affiliated Rural Institute on Disabilities
People with disabilities; Rural health services; Health services accessibility
Colleges and Universities; Montana
- MonTECH pamphlets, 1977, circa 1990s (File 1/1)
- Research and Training Center pamphlets, 1986-1990 and undated (File 1/2)
- The Rural Exchange, 1988-1994, 2008 (File 1/3)
- The Assistive Technologies Bulletin, 1989-1990 (File 1/4)
- Meeting the Rehabilitation Needs of Rural Americans, 1989 (File 1/5)
- Acceptance Is Only the First Battle: How Some Parents of Young Handicapped Children Have Coped with Common Problems, 1990 (File 1/6)
- Educational Home Model Project child-care booklets, 1990-1992 (File 1/7)
- Educational Home Model Project child-care booklets, 1990-1992 (File 1/8)
- Gerontology: Campus and Community Activities and Resources, 1990 (File 1/9)
- Rural Institute pamphlets, 1990-1994, circa 2000s (File 1/10)
- Rural Transition Issues: Report of the Rehabilitation Facility Survey, 1990 (File 1/11)
- Transitions from Rehabilitation Hospital to Rural Independent Living: Survey Results from Rural Independent Living Centers, circa 1990 (File 1/12)
- Child Care Plus, 1991-1993 (File 1/13)
- MonTECH News, 1992-1993 (File 1/14)
- MonTECH News, 1993-1994 (File MC/OS 3)
- MSED Quarterly, 1992-1993 (File 1/15)
- Removing Barriers: A Guide to Providing Substance Abuse Services to Those with Developmental Disabilities, 1993 (File 2/1)
- Seizure Disorders and Medications: A Self-paced Instructional Manual, 1993 (File 2/2)
- Ruralfacts, 1995-2006 and undated (File 2/3)
- American Indian Approaches to Disability Policy: Establishing Legal Protections for Tribal Members with Disabilities: Five Case Studies, 1996 (File 2/4)
- Progress Report, 1998-2006 (File 2/5)
- common threads, 1999-2000 (File 2/6)
- Emery County Business and Economic Development Assessment: 2000-2001 (File 2/7)
- Rural Practices Guidelines, 2001-2004 (File 2/8)
- Rural Civic Leadership and Disability: Positive Perspectives on Participation and Advocacy, 2004 (File 2/9)
- Policy Brief, 2006 (File 2/10)
- Montana Disability and Health Update, 2014 (File 2/11)
- Research that Leads to Solutions for Rural Americans with Disabilities, 2017 (File Electronic File)